Guide to the Franz R. and Kathryn M. Stenzel Collection of Western American Art Addition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Franz R. and Kathryn M. Stenzel Collection of Western American Art Addition
1853-1962
WA MSS S-2601
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
17
(12 boxes) + 13 art storage items, 1 object storage item, 2 broadsides
The Franz R. and Kathryn M. Stenzel Collection of Western American Art Addition consists of thirty-two works of art, twenty Native American artifacts, and various prints and manuscript items, which decorated the home of Kathryn M. Stenzel until her death in 2006 and which comprise the remainder of the art collection that was donated in 1997.
Stenzel, Franz
Bierstadt, Albert, 1830-1902
Catlin, George, 1796-1872
Darley, Felix Octavius Carr, 1822-1888
Eastman, Harrison, approximately 1823-
Harnett, William Michael, 1848-1892
Miller, Alfred Jacob, 1810-1874
Paxson, E. S., 1852-1919
Remington, Frederic, 1861-1909
Rockwell, Cleveland, 1837-1907
Roesen, Severin, approximately 1815-approximately 1872
Russell, Charles M. (Charles Marion), 1864-1926
Stanley, John Mix, 1814-1872
Stenzel, Kathryn M. (Kathryn Mathison)
Wiggins, Guy C. (Guy Carleton), 1883-1962
Wores, Theodore, 1858-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Kathryn M. Stenzel, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Associated material includes the Franz R. and Kathryn M. Stenzel Collection of Western American Art, WA MSS S-2368 and the Franz R. and Kathryn M. Stenzel Research Files on Western American Art, WA MSS S-2369. Books from the Stenzel library are cataloged separately, with the provenance traced.
Franz Robert Stenzel (1906-1998)
Dr. Franz Stenzel, a Portland, Oregon physician and one of the foremost authorities on early art of the Pacific Northwest, was born March 8, 1906 in Aberdeen, Washington. Two years later his family moved to Portland, where he would spend most of his life. He graduated from Bates College in 1933, and attended Harvard Medical School, studying internal medicine and specializing in cardiology. After working for nine years in Boston, he returned to Portland in 1946, where he entered private practice and was on the staff of Good Samaratin Hospital until his retirement in 1970. He also served as an instructor in cardiology at the University of Oregon Medical School, and became President of the Oregon Society of Internal Medicine.
Dr. Stenzel married Kathryn Marie Mathison in 1951 and the couple began collecting art of the American Northwest in 1955 after Dr. Stenzel was given a painting by a patient. While amassing a collection that eventually included approximately 2500 works of art, Dr. Stenzel became an authority on the early pictorial art of the Northwest, specializing in the period between 1800 and 1950. Research done while investigating sources for their collection evolved into a projected book on artists born before 1900 who worked in Washington, Oregon, Montana, Wyoming, southern British Columbia, and southern Alberta. Though this book was never published, research for this book contributed to his studies of two prominent Northwest artists: Cleveland Rockwell, Scientist and Artist, 1837-1907 (Portland, Or.: Oregon Historical Society, 1972) and James Madison Alden, Yankee Artist of the Pacific Coast, 1854-1860 (Fort Worth: Amon Carter Museum, 1975).
As an expert in his field, Dr. Stenzel was often called upon to give lectures and advice. He also wrote the text of several exhibition catalogues. Another offshoot of Dr. Stenzel's collecting was an interest in art restoration, a skill he taught himself. He constructed a conservation studio in his basement, which may be seen in an April 13, 1959 Life magazine article.
Works from the Stenzels' collection were exhibited many times, including major exhibits at the Amon Carter Museum, the Cheney Cowles Memorial Museum in Spokane, the Montana Historical Society, the Museum of Art at the University of Oregon, Eugene, and the Portland Art Museum. In 1973, four Stenzel pieces were the only privately owned art included in the first art exhibit by the United States Information Agency shown in former communist countries since World War II. Over the years, the Stenzels donated pieces of their collection to the C.M. Russell Gallery, the Montana Historical Society, the Oregon Historical Society, the Alaska State University in College, Alaska. In addition, the Stenzels offered 206 works of art for sale at a Sotheby's sale in Los Angeles June 24, 1980.
Dr. Stenzel died March 29, 1998 in Portland, Oregon at age 92, after a long illness. Mrs. Stenzel passed away in 2006.
Scope and Contents
The Franz R. and Kathryn M. Stenzel Collection of Western American Art Addition consists of thirty-two works of art, twenty Native American artifacts, and various manuscript items, which decorated the home of Kathryn M. Stenzel until her death in 2007 and which comprise the remainder of the Franz R. and Kathryn M. Stenzel Collection of Western American Art that they donated in 1997. This addition to the collection likewise reflects the Stenzels' interest in visual imagery of the American Northwest of the 19th and early 20th centuries. Included are works by Charles Marion Russell, Cleveland Rockwell, Albert Bierstadt, George Catlin, F. O. C. Darley, Harrison Eastman, William Harnett, Alfred Jacob Miller, E. S. Paxson, Frederic Remington, Severin Roesen, John Mix Stanley, Guy Wiggins, and Theodore Wores. The works are executed in a variety of media: oil paintings, watercolors, pen-and-ink drawings, chromolithographs, and sculpture. The Native American artifacts include clay urns, rattles, masks, carved totems, fishing hooks, a leather drum, a drum stick-rock, a quirt, a spear, a carved seal club, a pre-Columbian pot, a pestle, and a grease dish. The collection also includes Christmas cards designed by Charles Marion Russell as well as letters from him to Charles Joy and Charles Schatzlein.
Arrangement
The collection is largely organized by format or media.
Indians of North America -- Northwest, Pacific; Indians of North America -- Washington (State); Pioneers -- Washington (State); Northwest, Pacific -- Pictorial works; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Chromolithographs; Drawings (visual works); Oil paintings (visual works); Sculpture (visual works); Watercolors (paintings); Stenzel, Franz; Stenzel, Kathryn M. (Kathryn Mathison)
- Prints and Manuscript Items
  - Miller, Alfred Jacob
    - "Indian women washing hair", Chromolithograph, 5" x 7" (Box 1)
    - "Indian with white horse, camp", Chromolithograph, 5" x 7" (Box 1)
  - Russell, Charles Marion
    - Letter to Charles Joys, his night riding partner, with illustrations and explanations of three paintings in collection (Box 1)
    - Christmas cards, 1922, 1924, undated; (4 items) (Box 1)
    - Christmas card and envelope addressed to Mrs. Emma Schatzlein, 1917 (Box 1)
    - Letter to Charles Schatzlein regarding art work and supplies, 2 March 189- (Box 1)
- Sculpture
  - Russell, Charles Marion, Horse mounted on rock, with inscription "To Franz Stenzel, M. D. This rare C. M. Russell bronze is given in appreciation for dedication to the Historical Society of Montana" (Box 2)
- Artifacts
  - Clay urns, (2 items) (Box 2)
  - Rattles (Haida?), painted black faces with red features, (2 items) (Box 3)
  - Mask, unpainted, small amount of black showing, eyes, mouth and nostrils are slits (Box 3)
  - Argillite 11" carved totems, (2 items) (Box 4)
  - Carved raven ceremonial mask, Indian red. Bark hair is missing. (Box 4)
    General note
    James Gilchrist Swan gave this mask to Isaac Stevens, first Governor of Washington Territory. The Stenzels obtained it through Isaac Stevens's family.
  - Complete halibut hook carved with frog design, all bound together (Box 5)
  - Rectangular tray decorated at each end with two painted eyes, yellow, black, and green (Box 5)
  - Drum stick-rock encased in leather, decorated with horse tail (Box 6)
  - Quirt decorated in geometric pattern, ending in two shortened strips of leather (Box 6)
  - Carved front of halibut hook, in shape of man. Back of halibut hook is missing. (Box 6)
  - Spear, leather thong, metal and ivory (Box 6)
  - Carved seal club decorated with seals, Haida., circa 1880-1900 (Box 6)
  - Pre-Columbian pot with incised design (Box 6)
  - Pestle (Box 6)
  - Leather drum, undecorated (Box 7)
  - Small grease dish, with turned handle and of different wood than the grease dish (Box 7)
  - Argillite 8" eagle (Box 7)
- Watercolors, Drawings and Prints
  - Bryce, R., "Homesteading in Washington Ter.", Watercolor, 30.5 x 40.6 cm. (Box 8)
  - Eastman, Harrison, "Point Agate, trading post", Watercolor, 1874; 28.9 x 66.4 cm. (Box 27 (Broadside))
  - F. A., "Indians fishing in and ashore Queets River, WA", Watercolor, 1897; 14 x 27.9 cm. (Box 8)
  - Paxson, Egar S., "Assiniboine Warrior", Watercolor, 1905; 27.9 x 19.1 cm. (Box 8)
  - Rockwell, Cleveland, "Boats ashore Columbia River", Watercolor, 1902; 35.6 x 50.8 cm. (Box 28 (Broadside))
  - Stanley, John Mix
    - "Bois de Souix. Plate 7 vol XII, USPRR", Watercolor, 1853; 21.6 x 29.2 cm. (Box 9)
    - "Bear's Paw. Plate 23 vol XII, USPRR", Watercolor, 1853; 16.5 x 22.2 cm. (Box 9)
  - Schatzlein, Charles, "Indian warriors", Watercolor, signed "Chas. Schatzlein, Copy from Russell 1906", 33 x 45.7 cm. (Box 9)
  - Russell, Charles Marion
    - "Wagon train, white man's teepees", Black and white watercolor, 1903; 26.7 x 35.6 cm. (Box 10)
    - "Men who packed the flintlocks", Black and white watercolor, 1903; 26.7 x 36.8 cm. (Box 10)
    - "Blackfoot in Sioux Country", Black and white watercolor, 1903; 25.4 x 36.8 cm. (Box 10)
    - "Lone Wolf, Piegan", Watercolor, 1906; 30.5 x 22.9 cm. (Box 11)
    - "Buffalo Hunt #19", Watercolor, 1888; 21.6 x 27.9 cm. (Box 11)
    - "The Death of Trampus (book, The Virginian)", Pen and ink drawing, 35.6 x 30.5 cm. (Box 11)
  - Print "C. M. Russell and O. Seltzer"-colored. Copyright E. E. McGilvra, 1962; 33 x 48.3 cm. (Box 11)
- Oil Painting (unframed)
  - Remington, Frederic, "Indians with teepees", 25.4 x 30.5 cm. (Box 12)
- Oil Paintings (framed), (13 items)
  - Bierstadt, Albert, "Columbia River Scene", 34.3 x 48.3 cm., in frame 49.5 x 63.5 cm. (Box 13)
  - Catlin, George, "Portrait Orville Hungerford", 41.9 x 34.3 cm., in frame 57.2 x 47.6 cm. (Box 14)
  - Cox, Charles Brinton, "Mount Hood from Government Camp (Theo Roosevelt, Gen. Miles, Indian fighter, Burroughs, the naturalist, Col. Simmons, Commandant Ft. Vancouver)", 33 x 45.7 cm., in frame 54.6 x 65.4 cm. (Box 15)
  - Darley, F. O. C., "The Captive", 61 x 45.7 cm., in frame 73.7 x 59.1 cm. (Box 16)
  - Harnett, William M., "Still life. Pipe, tobacco, matches, news papers", 19.1 x 24.1 cm., in frame 27.9 x 33 cm. (Box 17)
  - Hill, T., "Indians, canoes on shores Sandy River, Ore.", 36.2 x 54 cm., in frame 50.2 x 66 cm. (Box 18)
  - Rockwell, Cleveland, "Crossing the Columbia River Bar", 76.2 x 127 cm., in frame 96.5 x 147.3 cm. (Box 19)
  - Roesen, Severin, "Still life with fruit", 63.5 x 76.2 cm., in frame 81.3 x 94 cm. (Box 20)
  - Russell, Charles Marion, "Roping a Bolter", 35.6 x 63.5 cm., in frame 54 x 82.6 cm. (Box 21)
  - Stuart, James Everett, "Neah Bay, WT", 45.7 x 76.2 cm., in frame 64.8 x 95.9 cm. (Box 22)
  - Wettland, S., "Joseph Pulitzer, bar pilot sailing ship at mouth of Columbia", 48.3 x 71.1 cm., in frame 61 x 81.3 cm. (Box 23)
  - Wiggins, Guy, "Madison Square", 29.2 x 39.4 cm., in frame 43.2 x 53.3 cm. (Box 24)
  - Wores, Theodore, "Little Chief of Creek Indians, Calgary", 25.4 x 21 cm., in frame 36.2 x 31.1 cm. (Box 25)
- Sculpture (oversize)
  - Procter, Alexander Phimster, "The Bucking Bronco", signed: AP Proctor 1915. Cast for J. G. Edwards. Life size bronco is in the Civic Center, Denver, Colorado., 69.9 x 54.6 cm. (Box 26)